Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting Yale University Women
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Oral histories documenting Yale University women
2007-2009
RU 1051
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.46
23 envelopes
44744.96
The materials consist of audio recordings and transcripts of oral history interviews conducted by Florence Minnis with women faculty, administrators, and staff affiliated with Yale University.
Abell, Millicent D.
Ameling, Ann
Borroff, Marie
Doane, Winifred W.
Eisenstein, Hester
Farley, Margaret A., 1935-
Forsberg, Joan Bates
Gersick, Connie J. G.
Haseltine, Florence
Hoffleit, Dorrit, 1907-
Kirk, Elizabeth D.
Mahar, Maggie
Minnis, Florence
Morse, Charlotte C., 1942-
Phillips, Rolly
Polan, Mary Lake
Quilligan, Maureen, 1944-
Singer, Dorothy G.
Skinner, H. Catherine W.
Spacks, Patricia Meyer, 1929-
Trachtenberg, Betty Glassman
Wasserman, Elga
Wei, Jacqueline
Wynne, Marjorie G.
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 49 (YRG 49), Papers and projects on Yale.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the materials is partially restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
Florence Minnis is the Director of the Yale Women's Oral History Project, Manuscripts and Archives. Before coming to Yale, she worked for many years in British television, specializing in social historical documentary film. (See Collection Contents for detailed biographical notes about the interviewees.)
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of sound recordings and edited transcripts of oral history interviews conducted by Florence Minnis with women faculty, administrators, and staff affiliated with Yale University. The edited transcripts, produced for readability, do not closely match the audiorecordings.
Administrative files relating to the project are maintained as part of Administrative Records of the Dept. of Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University (RU 129), Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Affirmative action programs; Coeducation; Sex discrimination against women; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Faculty; Women college students; Women college teachers; Women graduate students; Women in higher education; Women in science; Audiotapes; Oral histories (document genres); Abell, Millicent D.; Ameling, Ann; Borroff, Marie; Doane, Winifred W.; Eisenstein, Hester; Farley, Margaret A., 1935-; Forsberg, Joan Bates; Gersick, Connie J. G.; Haseltine, Florence; Hoffleit, Dorrit, 1907-; Kirk, Elizabeth D.; Mahar, Maggie; Morse, Charlotte C., 1942-; Phillips, Rolly; Polan, Mary Lake; Quilligan, Maureen, 1944-; Singer, Dorothy G.; Skinner, H. Catherine W.; Spacks, Patricia Meyer, 1929-; Trachtenberg, Betty Glassman; Wasserman, Elga; Wei, Jacqueline; Wynne, Marjorie G.; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- History -- 20th Century
- Hoffleit, Dorrit, 2007 February 8; Accession 2007-A-216
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  Biographical / Historical
  Dr. Dorrit E. Hoffleit was born on March 12, 1907, in Florence, Alabama. Her parents were German immigrants. In her early years she struggled to make her mark in the shadow of her brilliant though loving older brother and her mother's disappointment that her second child was "only a girl." Hoffleit reflects with characteristic optimism that these challenges were "blessings in disguise" which taught her both a resolute independence and a capacity for hard work. She graduated from Radcliffe College in 1928. Having failed to find employment as a teacher of mathematics she took a job at Harvard College Observatory as one of the "Harvard Computers," earning forty cents an hour to her male colleagues one dollar, but she flourished under the mentorship of the Director Harlow Shapley. Under his direction she earned her PH.D. from Radcliffe in 1938, for which she won the Caroline Wilby Prize for the best original research. Her association with Harvard Observatory, first as an assistant, then research associate and, from 1948, as astronomer, continued until 1956.
  After war service at the Ballistic Research Laboratories at the Aberdeen Proving Ground, Maryland, Hoffleit returned to Harvard to develop her thesis work on meteors and bright stars. In 1956 she left Harvard when Harlow Shapley retired and joined Yale as a research associate (subsequently, Senior Research Astronomer and Lecturer) at the Yale Observatory, where she authored the Yale Catalog of Bright Stars, the most popular catalog in astronomy. Her prodigious output also included the Yale Parallax Catalog, several volumes of the Yale Zone Catalog and many hundreds of papers on astronomy. Although she officially retired from Yale in 1975, she continued her research on variable stars and in 1988 her Bright Star catalog won the George van Biesbroeck Award for dedication to astronomy. While at Yale, Dr. Hoffleit directed the summer school on Nantucket at the Maria Mitchell Observatory, where she gave many young women scientists their first experience in astronomical research. For this she was awarded the American Astronomical Society-Annenberg Prize for science education in 1993. In 2003 she was made Senior Research Astronomer Emerita at Yale Observatory.
  Dr. Hoffleit's many awards include honorary degrees from Smith College (1984) and Central Connecticut State University (1998). She was inducted into the Connecticut Women's Hall of Fame in 1998. She was a past president of the American Association of Variable Star Observers. Asteroid Dorrit was named after her, and a Hoffleit Assistantship was established at the Mitchell Observatory to honor her work.
  Her interview for the Yale Women's Oral History Project was recorded shortly before her 100th birthday. Dorrit Hoffleit died April 9, 2007.
  Scope and Contents
  In her interview Dorrit Hoffleit talked at length about her early life and influences. Her mother's disappointment at producing "only" a daughter left its mark. Dr. Hoffleit reflected, "And so I was only the girl all my life, even to this day… People didn't expect so much of me, so I could work at my own pace." As a young girl during World War I she suffered anti-German bullying which made her something of a loner. Dr. Hoffleit never married, partly because her mother was unhappily married and partly because she feared that might pass on her grandmother's mental illness to subsequent generations.
  For her the most important issue, much more important than status and salary, was the independence she needed to follow her intellectual passions: "Having as much independence as I did in astronomy … was really something precious, very precious."
  - Audiorecording, 2007 February 8; 105; ; 1 hour and 45 minutes
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 1.1Ua–1.1Ub)
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Singer, Dorothy, 2007 April 10; Accession 2007-A-225
  Dorothy G. Singer was born in New York City on February 4, 1927, and grew up in Riverdale, New York. After attending Walton High School in the Bronx, one of the first all-girls high schools in New York, she went to Hunter College, where she developed a passion for the classics. She graduated with an A.B. in Humanities in 1948. Shortly after graduation she met Jerome L. Singer, and they married the following year. She won, but did not take, a fellowship to study archaeology at the Institute of Fine Arts in New York City. Instead the young couple moved to Philadelphia where Jerome Singer continued to pursue his Ph.D. in psychology. Dorothy Singer worked for an advertising agency but also took courses at Temple University, including psychology. When the couple moved back to New York, she undertook a part-time Master's degree in psychology at New York University, graduating in 1952, shortly before the birth of her first child.
  She postponed further academic pursuits until her third child was in kindergarten, when she enrolled in the Columbia University's Teachers' College doctoral program. There she was mentored by Morton Deutsch. She graduated in 1966 with a Ph.D. in School Psychology, and worked in a variety of research and counseling positions until 1968 when she joined Manhattanville College to teach psychology. She became department chair in 1972 but then left to take up a joint appointment in psychology at the University of Bridgeport and Yale University, her husband having accepted a professorship at Yale. At Bridgeport she developed many interdisciplinary courses, becoming the William Benton Professor of Psychology and eventually chair of the department. She left Bridgeport in 1990 to devote more time to her work as co-director of the Yale University Family Television Research and Consultation Center, which she and her husband had founded in 1975. The Center's work made a major contribution to the debate on the effect of television on children's learning and behavior. The Singers designed a national television curriculum for teenagers and conducted a major study for the United States Congress on educational programming for children. In addition to her work as co-director of the Center, since 1976 Dorothy Singer has been a Senior Research Scientist in the Department of Psychology and the Child Study Center at Yale University, where she is a distinguished teacher as well as researcher.
  Dorothy Singer has contributed over 130 articles on child psychology, media and communication, and written or co-authored many books, including Handbook of Children, Culture and Violence (Sage Publications, 2006) and Play=Learning (Oxford University Press, 2006). She has been a consultant to dozens of corporations including HBO and Walt Disney. She received the 1997 Distinguished Contribution to the Science of Psychology Award from the Connecticut Psychological Association and in 2006, the Distinguished Alumni Award from Teachers' College, Columbia University.
  Dorothy Singer talks extensively about an academic career which has spanned over forty years, and in particular reflects at length on the challenges she encountered in balancing family life and duties with her professional needs and aspirations, and on the choices she made. She also talks about her love of teaching and research, especially of the interdisciplinary and collaborative kind, and student mentoring. She speaks about tenure issues, salary differentials, nepotism rules, discrimination against women in academic publishing, and how these matters have either impacted her personally or academic women in general. She considers the ways in which life has changed for women in academia in her lifetime, the advances made, and what changes she believes need to be made to achieve gender and racial equality in academic life at Yale and beyond. In addition, she talks at some length about her early life, particularly her mother's influence. She also describes her experience of American suburban culture as a young mother in the 1950s and early 1960s.
  - Audiorecording, 2007; 75; ; 1 hour and 15 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 1.1U)
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 1)
- Abell, Penny, 2010 March 25; Accession 2012-A-035
  Permission to access must be obtained from interviewee until March 25, 2015.
  Millicent ("Penny") Demmin Abell was born February 15, 1934, in Wichita, Kansas. In 1945 her father died suddenly and her mother immediately moved the family to Colorado. The family was peripatetic for several years, but finally settled in Colorado Springs when Abell was a junior in high school. She attended Colorado College on a scholarship, and took a B.A. in 1956 after having dropped out for a year owing to illness. She had hoped to become a doctor but was dissuaded by her teachers on the grounds that it was too difficult for women to succeed in medicine. Instead, Abell went to Columbia University for a master's degree in student personnel work. She worked first at Duke University and then Arizona State University, where she was Assistant Dean of Women for two years.
  In 1962 Penny Abell married Julian ("Buck") Abell, a career military officer, and from that time she assumed that her career would fit around her husband's. When he was posted to West Point Military Academy, she worked there as a reference librarian, and, in 1965, took a Master's in Library Science at SUNY, Albany, in order to give her a portable career. When Buck Abell was sent overseas, she resigned and joined him in Bangkok. There she found work at the Institute for International Education and took the opportunity to travel extensively in Southeast Asia.
  The Abells returned to the U.S. in 1966. Abell took a job as Reference Librarian at Penrose Public Library, Colorado Springs, where her husband was then based, but she soon decided that she wanted to enter academic librarianship. This led her to complete a Master's in Political Science at the University of Colorado in 1969. During this time the Abells had a son. The family moved to Seattle in 1969 when Julian Abell, having left the army, returned to graduate studies. Penny Abell was hired as Assistant Librarian in the Business Administration Library at the University of Washington, Seattle, and in 1971 was promoted to Assistant Director of Libraries at the University of Washington. In 1973, she became the Associate Director of University Libraries at SUNY, Buffalo. From that moment, her career became the primary one in the Abell family. In 1976, she was sought out as University Librarian at the University of California, San Diego, where she remained until 1985, when she was appointed University Librarian at Yale University. She retired from Yale in 1994.
  Penny Abell was active in national and international library organizations. She was a founding member of both the Commission on Preservation and Access and the Digital Preservation Consortium. She was on the Board of Directors of the Center for Research Libraries, 1979-1986, and its chair, 1984-1985. Abell also served on the Board of Governors of the Research Libraries Group in 1985, and was a member of the executive committee, 1986-1991.
  In addition, she was a consultant prior to and following her retirement, advising university administrators and libraries at many institutions, including Columbia, Harvard and Toronto universities, and the New York Public Library. In 1998 she was called upon to serve as interim director of the University of California Berkeley Library.
  Penny Abell begins her interview by looking back on her childhood and the effect her father's early death had on the family and how it continued to reverberate in her own life as a young adult. She then briefly discusses her education and career aspirations, describing her college education and early professional life in student personnel management. On a number of occasions throughout the interview Abell explores how she and her husband negotiated their careers within their marriage. An explanation is given of why she decided to switch careers and become a librarian.
  The greater part of the interview traces her subsequent career as a senior administrator in academic libraries, first at SUNY, Buffalo, then University of California at San Diego, and finally and in most detail, her years as the University Librarian at Yale. A recurrent theme is the challenges women in senior management faced in the academic environment, with many examples given from her own experience. For example, she describes how her senior male colleagues responded to Title IX, the role a pregnancy may have played in compromising her first major promotion, and what it was like for much of her professional career to be often the only woman at meetings. She examines how feminism from Betty Friedan onwards informed her life and her ambivalence towards second wave feminism.
  Reflecting back on her career at Yale, she discusses the challenges of being the first female University Librarian at Yale, and her relationships with Yale faculty and administration. She recalls how she got the job, and her relationship with Bart Giamatti, then president of Yale. She addresses specific issues in the library wherein gender (and sometimes race) was to some extent a complicating factor. These included many budgetary and personnel challenges, including: the management of the Walpole Library; the aftermath of the 1984-1985 ten-week strike by clerical and technical workers belonging to the Local 34 union (which ended shortly before she took up her position at Yale); gender relationships within Yale Library, which had the largest concentration of women employees within the university (in managerial and professional as well as clerical positions), and the sources of conflict between her and her senior management team. Further, she discusses her relationships with other senior women at Yale, including Provosts Judith Rodin and Alison Richard. Abell recalls the regular informal meetings she had with Richard, when she was Director of the Peabody Museum, Mimi Neill (now Gates) who then was Director of Yale University Art Gallery, and Stephanie Spangler, the Director of University Health Services. The purpose of these meetings was mutual help, support, networking and mentoring, as well as political strategizing. She also pays tribute to Diane Turner and her contribution to changing labor relations within the Library. Continuing with the theme of mentoring, Abell acknowledges the support and mentoring of a number of men at Yale, especially Charles "Chip" Long in the Provost's Office, and Jaroslav Pelikan, Sterling Professor of History.
  Abell concludes the segment on Yale by talking about what she regards as her greatest achievements as University Librarian, her commitment to changing what she terms the cultural dynamics of the Library, and why she left Yale. Finally, in the course of the interview, Abell talks at length about the evolution of her own management style, her views on the qualities required for effective leadership, and how these may be best nurtured in women.
  - Audiorecording, 4; ; 4 hours and 15 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Ameling, Ann, 2008 June 27; Accession 2012-A-036
  Ann Tomaino Ameling was born in 1941 and grew up in Danbury, Connecticut. She was the only child of an Italian-American father who won a scholarship to Yale College (Class '25). He subsequently trained at Yale Medical School. Her mother was a nurse at Yale-New Haven Hospital, who gave up her job upon marriage. In 1962 Ameling graduated from Smith College, with a major in psychology. Her family discouraged her from following her father's profession, and she rejected the academic life because she saw that very few women attained tenure at that time. So Ameling opted for a career in nursing. Having earned a nursing degree from the Columbia University School of Nursing, she then worked at the Payne Whitney Psychiatric Institute at the Cornell Medical Center, New York. In 1965 Ameling entered Yale School of Nursing to take a Master of Science degree in Nursing, specializing in psychiatric nursing.
  Immediately following her graduation in 1967 Ameling joined the faculty at the Yale School of Nursing as a lecturer. She was an assistant professor 1970-1976, associate professor from 1976-1985, and tenured in 1984. During this time she was one of the first nursing school faculty (apart from deans) to become a fellow at a Yale residential college. Subsequently Ameling spent a semester as Acting Master at Berkeley College, and then was appointed Master of Saybrook College, serving 1985-1990. She joined Yale's central administration in 1989 as Associate Provost in charge of the School of Nursing, the School of Music, the Divinity School, the School of Forestry, the Center for British Art, the Yale Art Gallery, the residential colleges, and a number of academic departments including Classics, Religious Studies, Judaic and Near Eastern Studies. After more than a decade in Yale University's central administration, she returned to full-time teaching at the Nursing School. During this time she devoted much of her time to curriculum development, developing alternative and complementary therapies and end-of-life care as part of a multi-disciplinary Spirituality and Health curriculum. These innovations were funded by a grant from the Templeton Foundation and were taught in the Medical and Divinity Schools as well as in the Nursing School. After her retirement in 2003, Ameling returned to Yale as a student, this time at the Divinity School, to train as a United Church of Christ minister.
  In the early part of her career at the Yale nursing school, she worked extensively in the area of chronic psychiatric illness, and was the Principal Investigator on one of the first funded research projects evaluating psychiatric nursing care with the chronically ill psychiatric outpatient population (United States Psychiatric Health Service, 1970-1975). Ameling is the author of many articles on chronic psychiatric illness. Her 1982 book (with Yale colleague Judith Krauss), The Chronically Ill Psychiatric Outpatient in the Community, was named The American Journal of Nursing Book of the Year. She also has written a number of articles on spirituality and healing.
  Ann Ameling talks at length about her family background, particularly her childhood memories of Yale and her undergraduate experiences at Smith College, with special emphasis on its social culture. She recalls her early studies in nursing at Columbia University, her growing awareness of gender issues in medicine (especially obstetrics), and her subsequent experiences as a psychiatric nurse at the Payne Whitney Psychiatric Institute. The reasons why she chose Yale School of Nursing for her graduate work are then discussed, followed by an account of her experience of the Nursing School, first as a graduate student and then as a young faculty member. The school's internal culture is described, with reference to such issues as gender, sexism, and relationships between faculty and students. Its problematic external relations with the wider Yale community, especially with the Medical School, are addressed. Ameling also talks about the unique place of the school at Yale as a locus for high-achieving women and about the women on its faculty who became her role models or mentors, such as Florence Wald, Rita Dumas, Rachel Robinson, Margaret Arnstein and Donna Diers.